I study ants
[AI] 我研究蚂蚁
in the desert. in the tropical forest
[AI] 在沙漠里。在热带森林里
and in my kitchen.
[AI] 在我的厨房里。
and in the hills around Silicon Valley where I live.
[AI] 我住在硅谷周围的小山上。
I've recently realized that ants
[AI] 我最近意识到蚂蚁
are using interactions differently
[AI] 使用交互的方式是否不同
in different environments.
[AI] 在不同的环境中。
and that got me thinking that we could learn from this
[AI] 这让我想到我们可以从中学习
about other systems.
[AI] 关于其他系统。
like brains and data networks that we engineer.
[AI] 就像我们设计的大脑和数据网络。
and even cancer.
[AI] 甚至癌症。
So what all these systems have in common
[AI] 那么所有这些系统的共同点是什么呢
is that there's no central control.
[AI] 就是没有中央控制。
An ant colony consists of sterile female workers --
[AI] 蚁群由不育的女工组成--
those are the ants you see walking around —
[AI] 这些就是你看到的四处走动的蚂蚁
and then one or more reproductive females
[AI] 然后是一个或多个生殖雌性
who just lay the eggs.
[AI] 刚下蛋的人。
They don't give any instructions.
[AI] 他们不给任何指示。
Even though they're called queens.
[AI] 尽管他们被称为女王。
they don't tell anybody what to do.
[AI] 他们不告诉任何人该做什么。
So in an ant colony. there's no one in charge.
[AI] 所以在蚁群中。没有人负责。
and all systems like this without central control
[AI] 所有这样的系统都没有中央控制
are regulated using very simple interactions.
[AI] 使用非常简单的交互进行管理。
Ants interact using smell.
[AI] 蚂蚁利用气味进行互动。
They smell with their antennae.
[AI] 它们用触角闻气味。
and they interact with their antennae.
[AI] 它们与触角相互作用。
so when one ant touches another with its antennae.
[AI] 所以当一只蚂蚁用它的触角触碰另一只蚂蚁时。
it can tell. for example. if the other ant
[AI] 它可以告诉你。例如如果另一只蚂蚁
is a nestmate
[AI] 他是一个巢友
and what task that other ant has been doing.
[AI] 还有另一只蚂蚁在做什么。
So here you see a lot of ants moving around
[AI] 所以在这里你看到很多蚂蚁四处移动
and interacting in a lab arena
[AI] 在实验室里进行互动
that's connected by tubes to two other arenas.
[AI] 通过管道连接到另外两个竞技场。
So when one ant meets another.
[AI] 所以当一只蚂蚁遇到另一只蚂蚁。
it doesn't matter which ant it meets.
[AI] 遇到哪只蚂蚁并不重要。
and they're actually not transmitting
[AI] 实际上它们并没有传播
any kind of complicated signal or message.
[AI] 任何一种复杂的信号或信息。
All that matters to the ant is the rate
[AI] 对蚂蚁来说，重要的是速度
at which it meets other ants.
[AI] 在那里它遇到了其他蚂蚁。
And all of these interactions. taken together.
[AI] 所有这些互动。综合起来。
produce a network.
[AI] 产生一个网络。
So this is the network of the ants
[AI] 这就是蚂蚁的网络
that you just saw moving around in the arena.
[AI] 你刚才在竞技场里看到的。
and it's this constantly shifting network
[AI] 这是一个不断变化的网络
that produces the behavior of the colony.
[AI] 这就产生了群体的行为。
like whether all the ants are hiding inside the nest.
[AI] 比如是否所有的蚂蚁都躲在巢穴里。
or how many are going out to forage.
[AI] 或者有多少人出去觅食。
A brain actually works in the same way.
[AI] 大脑实际上也是这样工作的。
but what's great about ants is
[AI] 但是蚂蚁的优点是
that you can see the whole network as it happens.
[AI] 你可以看到整个网络，因为它发生了。
There are more than 12.000 species of ants.
[AI] 蚂蚁有12000多种。
in every conceivable environment.
[AI] 在任何可以想象的环境中。
and they're using interactions differently
[AI] 他们使用不同的交互方式
to meet different environmental challenges.
[AI] 以应对不同的环境挑战。
So one important environmental challenge
[AI] 这是一个重要的环境挑战
that every system has to deal with
[AI] 每个系统都必须处理的问题
is operating costs. just what it takes
[AI] 是运营成本。正是它所需要的
to run the system.
[AI] 运行系统。
And another environmental challenge is resources.
[AI] 另一个环境挑战是资源。
finding them and collecting them.
[AI] 找到并收集它们。
In the desert. operating costs are high
[AI] 在沙漠里。运营成本很高
because water is scarce.
[AI] 因为水是稀缺的。
and the seed-eating ants that I study in the desert
[AI] 还有我在沙漠里研究的吃种子的蚂蚁
have to spend water to get water.
[AI] 必须花钱才能得到水。
So an ant outside foraging.
[AI] 所以一只蚂蚁在外面觅食。
searching for seeds in the hot sun.
[AI] 在烈日下寻找种子。
just loses water into the air.
[AI] 只是把水丢到空气中。
But the colony gets its water
[AI] 但是殖民地得到了水
by metabolizing the fats out of the seeds
[AI] 通过代谢种子中的脂肪
that they eat.
[AI] 他们吃的东西。
So in this environment. interactions are used
[AI] 所以在这种环境下。使用交互
to activate foraging.
[AI] 激活觅食。
An outgoing forager doesn't go out unless
[AI] 外出觅食的人除非
it gets enough interactions with returning foragers.
[AI] 它与返回的觅食者有足够的互动。
and what you see are the returning foragers
[AI] 你看到的是返回的觅食者
going into the tunnel. into the nest.
[AI] 进入隧道。进入巢穴。
and meeting outgoing foragers on their way out.
[AI] 并在外出途中与外出觅食者会面。
This makes sense for the ant colony.
[AI] 这对蚁群来说是有意义的。
because the more food there is out there.
[AI] 因为外面的食物越多。
the more quickly the foragers find it.
[AI] 觅食者越快找到它。
the faster they come back.
[AI] 他们回来的越快。
and the more foragers they send out.
[AI] 他们派出的搜寻者越多。
The system works to stay stopped.
[AI] 系统工作以保持停止。
unless something positive happens.
[AI] 除非有积极的事情发生。
So interactions function to activate foragers.
[AI] 因此，交互作用可以激活觅食者。
And we've been studying the evolution of this system.
[AI] 我们一直在研究这个系统的演变。
First of all. there's variation.
[AI] 首先有变化。
It turns out that colonies are different.
[AI] 结果证明，殖民地是不同的。
On dry days. some colonies forage less.
[AI] 在干旱的日子里。有些殖民地觅食较少。
so colonies are different in how
[AI] 因此，殖民地在方式上是不同的
they manage this trade-off
[AI] 他们管理这一权衡
between spending water to search for seeds
[AI] 在花钱寻找种子之间
and getting water back in the form of seeds.
[AI] 以种子的形式把水弄回来。
And we're trying to understand why
[AI] 我们正在努力理解为什么
some colonies forage less than others
[AI] 一些殖民地的觅食量比其他殖民地少
by thinking about ants as neurons.
[AI] 把蚂蚁想象成神经元。
using models from neuroscience.
[AI] 使用神经科学的模型。
So just as a neuron adds up its stimulation
[AI] 就像神经元增加刺激一样
from other neurons to decide whether to fire.
[AI] 由其他神经元决定是否开火。
an ant adds up its stimulation from other ants
[AI] 蚂蚁把其他蚂蚁的刺激加起来
to decide whether to forage.
[AI] 决定是否饲草。
And what we're looking for is whether there might be
[AI] 我们要找的是是否有可能
small differences among colonies
[AI] 殖民地之间的微小差异
in how many interactions each ant needs
[AI] 每只蚂蚁需要多少交互
before it's willing to go out and forage.
[AI] 在它愿意出去觅食之前。
because a colony like that would forage less.
[AI] 因为那样的一个殖民地会吃得更少。
And this raises an analogous question about brains.
[AI] 这就提出了一个关于大脑的类似问题。
We talk about the brain.
[AI] 我们谈论大脑。
but of course every brain is slightly different.
[AI] 当然，每个人的大脑都略有不同。
and maybe there are some individuals
[AI] 也许有一些人
or some conditions
[AI] 或者一些条件
in which the electrical properties of neurons are such
[AI] 神经元的电特性是这样的
that they require more stimulus to fire.
[AI] 他们需要更多的刺激来激发。
and that would lead to differences in brain function.
[AI] 这将导致大脑功能的差异。
So in order to ask evolutionary questions.
[AI] 所以为了提出进化论的问题。
we need to know about reproductive success.
[AI] 我们需要了解生殖成功的情况。
This is a map of the study site
[AI] 这是研究地点的地图
where I have been tracking this population
[AI] 我一直在跟踪这些人口
of harvester ant colonies for 28 years.
[AI] 28年来收获机蚁群的数量。
which is about as long as a colony lives.
[AI] 这大约是一个殖民地的寿命。
Each symbol is a colony.
[AI] 每个符号都是一个殖民地。
and the size of the symbol is how many offspring it had.
[AI] 这个符号的大小是它有多少后代。
because we were able to use genetic variation
[AI] 因为我们能够利用遗传变异
to match up parent and offspring colonies.
[AI] 匹配亲代和后代群体。
that is. to figure out which colonies
[AI] 就是。找出哪个殖民地
were founded by a daughter queen
[AI] 是由一位女王的女儿创建的
produced by which parent colony.
[AI] 由哪个父群体产生的。
And this was amazing for me. after all these years.
[AI] 这对我来说太神奇了。这么多年过去了。
to find out. for example. that colony 154.
[AI] 去发现。例如那个殖民地是154。
whom I've known well for many years.
[AI] 我认识他很多年了。
is a great-grandmother.
[AI] 她是一位曾祖母。
Here's her daughter colony.
[AI] 这是她的女儿柯罗尼。
here's her granddaughter colony.
[AI] 这是她的孙女柯罗尼。
and these are her great-granddaughter colonies.
[AI] 这些是她的曾孙女。
And by doing this. I was able to learn
[AI] 通过这样做。我能够学习
that offspring colonies resemble parent colonies
[AI] 后代群体与亲代群体相似
in their decisions about which days are so hot
[AI] 他们决定哪天这么热
that they don't forage.
[AI] 他们不吃草。
and the offspring of parent colonies
[AI] 以及亲代群体的后代
live so far from each other that the ants never meet.
[AI] 蚂蚁们住得太远了，从来没有见过面。
so the ants of the offspring colony
[AI] 所以后代群体的蚂蚁
can't be learning this from the parent colony.
[AI] 不能从母殖民地那里学到这一点。
And so our next step is to look
[AI] 所以我们下一步要做的就是
for the genetic variation underlying this resemblance.
[AI] 因为这种相似性背后的遗传变异。
So then I was able to ask. okay. who's doing better?
[AI] 然后我就可以问了。可以谁做得更好？
Over the time of the study.
[AI] 在研究期间。
and especially in the past 10 years.
[AI] 尤其是在过去的10年里。
there's been a very severe and deepening drought
[AI] 这是一场非常严重且不断加深的干旱
in the Southwestern U.S..
[AI] 在美国西南部。。
and it turns out that the colonies that conserve water.
[AI] 事实证明，这些保护水源的殖民地。
that stay in when it's really hot outside.
[AI] 当外面真的很热的时候就呆在家里。
and thus sacrifice getting as much food as possible.
[AI] 从而牺牲了获得尽可能多的食物。
are the ones more likely to have offspring colonies.
[AI] 是那些更可能有后代的群体。
So all this time. I thought that colony 154
[AI] 所以一直以来。我以为殖民地154号
was a loser. because on really dry days.
[AI] 他是个失败者。因为在非常干燥的日子里。
there'd be just this trickle of foraging.
[AI] 这只是一点点的觅食。
while the other colonies were out
[AI] 当其他殖民地不在的时候
foraging. getting lots of food.
[AI] 觅食。得到很多食物。
but in fact. colony 154 is a huge success.
[AI] 但事实上。殖民地154是一个巨大的成功。
She's a matriarch.
[AI] 她是女族长。
She's one of the rare great-grandmothers on the site.
[AI] 她是网站上罕见的曾祖母之一。
To my knowledge. this is the first time
[AI] 据我所知。这是第一次
that we've been able to track
[AI] 我们能追踪到的
the ongoing evolution of collective behavior
[AI] 集体行为的持续演变
in a natural population of animals
[AI] 在动物的自然种群中
and find out what's actually working best.
[AI] 找出什么是最有效的。
Now. the Internet uses an algorithm
[AI] 现在互联网使用一种算法
to regulate the flow of data
[AI] 调节数据流
that's very similar to the one
[AI] 这和那个很相似
that the harvester ants are using to regulate
[AI] 收割机蚂蚁用来调节的
the flow of foragers.
[AI] 觅食者的流动。
And guess what we call this analogy?
[AI] 猜猜我们怎么称呼这个比喻？
The anternet is coming.
[AI] 蚂蚁网来了。
(Applause)
[AI] （掌声）
So data doesn't leave the source computer
[AI] 所以数据不会离开源计算机
unless it gets a signal that there's enough bandwidth
[AI] 除非它得到足够带宽的信号
for it to travel on.
[AI] 让它继续前行。
In the early days of the Internet.
[AI] 在互联网的早期。
when operating costs were really high
[AI] 当运营成本真的很高的时候
and it was really important not to lose any data.
[AI] 不丢失任何数据非常重要。
then the system was set up for interactions
[AI] 然后，系统被设置为交互
to activate the flow of data.
[AI] 激活数据流。
It's interesting that the ants are using an algorithm
[AI] 有趣的是蚂蚁正在使用一种算法
that's so similar to the one that we recently invented.
[AI] 这和我们最近发明的非常相似。
but this is only one of a handful of ant algorithms
[AI] 但这只是为数不多的蚂蚁算法之一
that we know about.
[AI] 我们所知道的。
and ants have had 130 million years
[AI] 蚂蚁已经有1.3亿年了
to evolve a lot of good ones.
[AI] 进化出很多好的。
and I think it's very likely
[AI] 我认为很有可能
that some of the other 12.000 species
[AI] 其他12000个物种中的一些
are going to have interesting algorithms
[AI] 我们将会有有趣的算法
for data networks
[AI] 用于数据网络
that we haven't even thought of yet.
[AI] 我们甚至还没想到。
So what happens when operating costs are low?
[AI] 那么，当运营成本较低时会发生什么呢？
Operating costs are low in the tropics.
[AI] 热带地区的运营成本很低。
because it's very humid. and it's easy for the ants
[AI] 因为天气很潮湿。这对蚂蚁来说很容易
to be outside walking around.
[AI] 在外面走来走去。
But the ants are so abundant
[AI] 但是蚂蚁太多了
and diverse in the tropics
[AI] 热带地区气候多样
that there's a lot of competition.
[AI] 有很多竞争。
Whatever resource one species is using.
[AI] 一个物种正在使用的任何资源。
another species is likely to be using that
[AI] 另一个物种很可能正在使用它
at the same time.
[AI] 同时
So in this environment. interactions are used
[AI] 所以在这种环境下。使用交互
in the opposite way.
[AI] 以相反的方式。
The system keeps going
[AI] 系统继续运行
unless something negative happens.
[AI] 除非有负面的事情发生。
and one species that I study makes circuits
[AI] 我研究的一个物种制造电路
in the trees of foraging ants
[AI] 在觅食蚂蚁的树上
going from the nest to a food source and back.
[AI] 从巢穴到食物来源再回来。
just round and round.
[AI] 一圈又一圈。
unless something negative happens.
[AI] 除非有负面的事情发生。
like an interaction
[AI] 就像一次互动
with ants of another species.
[AI] 和另一种蚂蚁在一起。
So here's an example of ant security.
[AI] 这里有一个蚂蚁安全的例子。
In the middle. there's an ant
[AI] 在中间有一只蚂蚁
plugging the nest entrance with its head
[AI] 用它的头堵住鸟巢的入口
in response to interactions with another species.
[AI] 为了回应与另一物种的相互作用。
Those are the little ones running around
[AI] 那些是到处跑的小家伙
with their abdomens up in the air.
[AI] 腹部悬空。
But as soon as the threat is passed.
[AI] 但一旦威胁过去。
the entrance is open again.
[AI] 入口又开了。
and maybe there are situations
[AI] 也许有些情况
in computer security
[AI] 计算机安全
where operating costs are low enough
[AI] 运营成本足够低的地方
that we could just block access temporarily
[AI] 我们可以暂时阻止访问
in response to an immediate threat.
[AI] 为了应对迫在眉睫的威胁。
and then open it again.
[AI] 然后再打开它。
instead of trying to build
[AI] 而不是试图建立
a permanent firewall or fortress.
[AI] 永久的防火墙或堡垒。
So another environmental challenge
[AI] 那么另一个环境挑战呢
that all systems have to deal with
[AI] 所有系统都必须处理的问题
is resources. finding and collecting them.
[AI] 这就是资源。寻找和收集它们。
And to do this. ants solve the problem
[AI] 这样做。蚂蚁解决了这个问题
of collective search.
[AI] 集体搜索的结果。
and this is a problem that's of great interest
[AI] 这是一个非常有趣的问题
right now in robotics.
[AI] 现在在机器人领域。
because we've understood that.
[AI] 因为我们明白这一点。
rather than sending a single.
[AI] 而不是发送一个。
sophisticated. expensive robot out
[AI] 复杂的昂贵的机器人
to explore another planet
[AI] 探索另一个星球
or to search a burning building.
[AI] 或者搜查燃烧的建筑物。
that instead. it may be more effective
[AI] 那倒是。它可能更有效
to get a group of cheaper robots
[AI] 为了得到一群更便宜的机器人
exchanging only minimal information.
[AI] 只交换最少的信息。
and that's the way that ants do it.
[AI] 蚂蚁就是这样做的。
So the invasive Argentine ant
[AI] 所以入侵的阿根廷蚂蚁
makes expandable search networks.
[AI] 创建可扩展的搜索网络。
They're good at dealing with the main problem
[AI] 他们擅长处理主要问题
of collective search.
[AI] 集体搜索的结果。
which is the trade-off between
[AI] 两者之间的权衡是什么
searching very thoroughly
[AI] 彻底搜查
and covering a lot of ground.
[AI] 覆盖了很多土地。
And what they do is.
[AI] 他们所做的是。
when there are many ants in a small space.
[AI] 当一个小空间里有很多蚂蚁时。
then each one can search very thoroughly
[AI] 然后每个人都可以非常彻底地搜索
because there will be another ant nearby
[AI] 因为附近会有另一只蚂蚁
searching over there.
[AI] 在那边搜索。
but when there are a few ants
[AI] 但是当有几只蚂蚁的时候
in a large space.
[AI] 在很大的空间里。
then they need to stretch out their paths
[AI] 然后他们需要扩展他们的道路
to cover more ground.
[AI] 覆盖更多的土地。
I think they use interactions to assess density.
[AI] 我认为他们用互动来评估密度。
so when they're really crowded.
[AI] 所以当他们真的很拥挤的时候。
they meet more often.
[AI] 他们见面更频繁。
and they search more thoroughly.
[AI] 而且他们搜索得更彻底。
Different ant species must use different algorithms.
[AI] 不同的蚂蚁物种必须使用不同的算法。
because they've evolved to deal with
[AI] 因为他们已经进化到可以处理
different resources.
[AI] 不同的资源。
and it could be really useful to know about this.
[AI] 了解这一点可能非常有用。
and so we recently asked ants
[AI] 所以我们最近问蚂蚁
to solve the collective search problem
[AI] 解决集体搜索问题
in the extreme environment
[AI] 在极端环境中
of microgravity
[AI] 微重力
in the International Space Station.
[AI] 在国际空间站。
When I first saw this picture. I thought.
[AI] 当我第一次看到这张照片的时候。我想。
Oh no. they've mounted the habitat vertically.
[AI] 哦，不，他们已经垂直安装了栖息地。
but then I realized that. of course. it doesn't matter.
[AI] 但后来我意识到了这一点。当然没关系。
So the idea here is that the ants
[AI] 所以这里的想法是蚂蚁
are working so hard to hang on
[AI] 你是如此努力地工作来坚持下去
to the wall or the floor or whatever you call it
[AI] 到墙上或地板上，或者你管它叫什么
that they're less likely to interact.
[AI] 他们不太可能互动。
and so the relationship between
[AI] 因此，它们之间的关系
how crowded they are and how often they meet
[AI] 他们有多拥挤，见面的频率有多高
would be messed up.
[AI] 会搞砸的。
We're still analyzing the data.
[AI] 我们还在分析数据。
I don't have the results yet.
[AI] 我还没有结果。
But it would be interesting to know
[AI] 但知道这一点会很有趣
how other species solve this problem
[AI] 其他物种如何解决这个问题
in different environments on Earth.
[AI] 在地球上不同的环境中。
and so we're setting up a program
[AI] 所以我们正在制定一个计划
to encourage kids around the world
[AI] 鼓励世界各地的孩子
to try this experiment with different species.
[AI] 用不同的物种做这个实验。
It's very simple.
[AI] 这很简单。
It can be done with cheap materials.
[AI] 这可以用便宜的材料来完成。
And that way. we could make a global map
[AI] 就这样。我们可以制作一张全球地图
of ant collective search algorithms.
[AI] 蚂蚁集体搜索算法。
And I think it's pretty likely that the invasive species.
[AI] 我认为很可能是入侵物种。
the ones that come into our buildings.
[AI] 那些进入我们大楼的人。
are going to be really good at this.
[AI] 你会在这方面做得很好的。
because they're in your kitchen
[AI] 因为它们在你的厨房里
because they're really good at finding food and water.
[AI] 因为他们真的很擅长寻找食物和水。
So the most familiar resource for ants
[AI] 所以蚂蚁最熟悉的资源
is a picnic.
[AI] 这是一次野餐。
and this is a clustered resource.
[AI] 这是一个集群资源。
When there's one piece of fruit.
[AI] 当有一片水果的时候。
there's likely to be another piece of fruit nearby.
[AI] 附近可能还有一块水果。
and the ants that specialize on clustered resources
[AI] 还有专门研究集群资源的蚂蚁
use interactions for recruitment.
[AI] 利用互动进行招聘。
So when one ant meets another.
[AI] 所以当一只蚂蚁遇到另一只蚂蚁。
or when it meets a chemical deposited
[AI] 或者当它遇到化学物质时
on the ground by another.
[AI] 被另一个人扔在地上。
then it changes direction to follow
[AI] 然后它改变方向以跟随
in the direction of the interaction.
[AI] 在互动的方向上。
and that's how you get the trail of ants
[AI] 你就是这样找到蚂蚁的踪迹的
sharing your picnic.
[AI] 分享你的野餐。
Now this is a place where I think we might be able
[AI] 现在我想我们可以在这里
to learn something from ants about cancer.
[AI] 从蚂蚁身上学到一些关于癌症的知识。
I mean. first. it's obvious that we could do a lot
[AI] 我是说。第一很明显，我们可以做很多
to prevent cancer
[AI] 预防癌症
by not allowing people to spread around
[AI] 不允许人们四处传播
or sell the toxins that promote
[AI] 或者出售促进健康的毒素
the evolution of cancer in our bodies.
[AI] 癌症在我们体内的演变。
but I don't think the ants can help us much with this
[AI] 但我认为蚂蚁在这方面帮不了我们多少忙
because ants never poison their own colonies.
[AI] 因为蚂蚁从不毒害自己的殖民地。
But we might be able to learn something from ants
[AI] 但我们或许可以从蚂蚁身上学到一些东西
about treating cancer.
[AI] 关于治疗癌症。
There are many different kinds of cancer.
[AI] 癌症有很多种。
Each one originates in a particular part of the body.
[AI] 每一个都起源于身体的特定部位。
and then some kinds of cancer will spread
[AI] 然后一些癌症就会扩散
or metastasize to particular other tissues
[AI] 或转移到特定的其他组织
where they must be getting resources that they need.
[AI] 他们必须得到他们需要的资源。
So if you think from the perspective
[AI] 所以如果你从这个角度来思考
of early metastatic cancer cells
[AI] 早期转移癌细胞的研究进展
as they're out searching around
[AI] 当他们在外面四处寻找的时候
for the resources that they need.
[AI] 他们需要的资源。
if those resources are clustered.
[AI] 如果这些资源是集群的。
they're likely to use interactions for recruitment.
[AI] 他们可能会利用互动进行招聘。
and if we can figure out how cancer cells are recruiting.
[AI] 如果我们能弄清楚癌细胞是如何招募的。
then maybe we could set traps
[AI] 也许我们可以设陷阱
to catch them before they become established.
[AI] 在他们建立之前抓住他们。
So ants are using interactions in different ways
[AI] 所以蚂蚁以不同的方式使用交互作用
in a huge variety of environments.
[AI] 在各种各样的环境中。
and we could learn from this
[AI] 我们可以从中学习
about other systems that operate
[AI] 关于其他运行的系统
without central control.
[AI] 没有中央控制。
Using only simple interactions.
[AI] 只使用简单的交互。
ant colonies have been performing
[AI] 蚁群一直在表演
amazing feats for more than 130 million years.
[AI] 超过1.3亿年的惊人壮举。
We have a lot to learn from them.
[AI] 我们有很多东西要向他们学习。
Thank you.
[AI] 非常感谢。
(Applause)
[AI] （掌声）